A Guide to the Governor John Tyler Executive Papers, 1808-1811
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Governor John Tyler Executive Papers, 1808-1811
Library of Virginia
41223
3.65 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reel 6006-6017.
Miscellaneous Reel 6006 - 1808 Dec.-1809 Feb. 28
Miscellaneous Reel 6007 - 1809 Mar. 2-May 31
Miscellaneous Reel 6008 - 1809 June 1-July 31
Miscellaneous Reel 6009 - 1809 Aug. 1-Sept. 30
Miscellaneous Reel 6010 - 1809 Oct. 2-Dec. 30
Miscellaneous Reel 6011 - 1810 Jan. 1-Feb. 28
Miscellaneous Reel 6012 - 1810 Mar. 1-Apr. 30
Miscellaneous Reel 6013 - 1810 May 1-June 30
Miscellaneous Reel 6014 - 1810 July 1-Aug. 30
Miscellaneous Reel 6015 - 1810 Sept. 1-Oct. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 6016 - 1810 Nov. 1-Dec. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 6017 - 1811 Jan. 1-15
Biographical Information
John Tyler, Sr., was born on 28 February 1747 in James City County to John Tyler and Ann Contesse. Tyler attended William and Mary College and later studied law under Robert Carter Nicholas. Tyler began practicing law in Charles City County in 1770. An ardent supporter of the Revolution, Tyler served as a member of the Committee of Safety for Charles City County in 1774 and raised a company of troops when Lord Dunmore removed the powder from the magazine at Williamsburg. In 1776, he was appointed to a one-year term as judge of the Court of Admiralty. Tyler was elected to represent Charles City County in the House of Delegates where he served from 1778 until 1786. While a member of the House of Delegates, Tyler succeeded Benjamin Harrison as Speaker of the House of Delegates in 1781, serving in that capacity until 1785. In addition, Tyler, along with James Madison, proposed a meeting of states in Annapolis in 1786 to discuss granting Congress to power to regulate commerce. The Annapolis Convention led to the Constitutional Convention of 1787 to revise the Articles of Confederation. In 1786, Tyler replaced Benjamin Waller as judge of the Court of Admiralty. As vice-president of the Virginia Convention of 1788, Tyler, a states-rights advocate, voted against the ratification of the Federal Constitution. Tyler was elected to the General Court in 1788 when the new Constitution assigned jurisdiction of the Court of Admiralty to the federal courts. Tyler served as judge of the General Court until 12 December 1808 when he was elected to succeed William H. Cabell as governor. Tyler was elected to two additional one-year terms, but resigned the governorship on 15 January 1811 in order to accept an appointment as judge of the Federal District Court for Virginia.
John Tyler married Mary Armistead, daughter of Robert Booth Armistead, in 1776. Their son, John Tyler, Jr., served as both governor of Virginia from 1825 to 1827 and as the 10th President of the United States from 1841 to 1845. Tyler died at "Greenway", his residence in Charles City County, on 6 January 1813.
Scope and Content
John Tyler's Executive papers primarily consist of incoming correspondence during his two one-year terms as governor between 12 December 1808 and 15 January 1811. The correspondence in this collection relates to a variety of topics including appointments & recommendations for state positions; the Virginia Manufactory of Arms; the Virginia Penitentiary; amendments to the U.S. Constitution; arms and ammunition; the militia; French inhabitants expelled from Cuba; the embargo; public improvements; resignations; extraditions; state expenses & revenue; elections; and others. In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions from the Virginia Senate & House of Delegates; accounts; oaths; contracts; pardons; proposals; receipts; election returns & certificates; qualifications; lists; proclamations; petitions; pay rolls; reports; appointments; resignations; bonds; commissions; orders; proceedings; opinions; and other sundry items.
The Governor received correspondence from three main sources: the Federal government, Virginia State government, and Governors from other states. Federal government correspondents include President Thomas Jefferson; Robert Smith, Secretary of State; Henry Dearborn & William Eustis, Secretaries of War; and Virginia's delegates in Congress. President Thomas Jefferson writes Governor Tyler on 20 Jan. 1809 regarding a letter from Henry St. John Dixon offering the services of his company of volunteer riflemen of the 105th Regiment. On 10 Aug. 1810, Robert Smith, Secretary of State, transmits copies of the laws of the 1st & 2nd session of the 11th Congress. As Secretary of War, Henry Dearborn, writes the Governor regarding the appointment of an officer of the militia near each point of entry to assemble a sufficient force to maintain the authority of the laws respecting the embargo (1809 Jan. 18). Dearborn also writes on 4 Feb. 1809 regarding Virginia's quota of militia. On 17 April 1809, William Eustis writes the Governor regarding pensioners. Eustis also encloses pay rolls and a letter from Robert Brent, Pay Master for the U.S. Army, regarding money paid by the U.S. to detachments of the Virginia Militia called into service in 1808 (1809 Dec. 7). Lastly, Eustis writes regarding land warrants issued by the state on lands already surveyed and sold to individuals by authority of the United States between the Little Miami & Scioto Rivers (1810 Dec. 19). In addition, there is a letter from William Simmons, War Dept., Accountant's Office, regarding tents furnished the militia during the Chesapeake Affair (1810 Jan. 11). William B. Giles & Richard Brent, Virginia's senators in Congress, write on 10 June 1809 regarding the French inhabitants expelled from Cuba and the importation of their slaves. Giles & Brent also write concerning a machine exhibited at the Capitol (1810 Feb. 6). Finally, Giles encloses the proceedings of a Committee of the U.S. Senate regarding the resolutions of the Virginia General Assembly on the subject of bounty lands to officers & soldiers of the Virginia State Line (1810 Nov. 1). There are also letters from both Wilson Cary Nicholas and John G. Jackson resigning from their seats in the U.S. House of Representatives (1809 Nov. 27 & 1810 Sept. 28).
The majority of correspondence in John Tyler's Executive Papers originates from Virginia State government. Significant correspondents from Virginia State government include John Clarke & John Staples, Superintendents of the Virginia Manufactory of Arms; Abraham Douglas, Keepers of the Penitentiary; Philip Norborne Nicholas, Attorney General; Daniel L. Hylton, Clerk of the Council; Samuel Coleman, Assistant Clerk of the Council of State; James Pleasants, Jr., Clerk of the House of Delegates; Theodosius Hansford, Clerk of the Senate; and Samuel Shepard, Auditor of Public Accounts.
John Clarke & John Staples, as Superintendents of the Virginia Manufactory of Arms, corresponded frequently with the Governor, regarding arms and the Manufactory in Richmond, Virginia. John Clarke provides a report of the number of arms at the Point of Fork Arsenal on 31 March 1792, the number of arms issued to the militia, the number of arms in the garret of the Capitol, etc. (1808 Dec. 19). Clarke also provides a statement of arms distributed to the militia since 27 April 1806 (1809 Jan. 13). Also included are correspondence related to the following subjects: the contract of Col. John Harvie to furnish bricks & lime for building the Manufactory of Arms (1809 Jan. 11); the repair of old arms in the garret of the Capitol (1809 Jan. 23); contracts for carpenter's work for the Foundry & Boring Mill (1809 March 28); and the price & quality of iron produced by Mr. Calloway for the Manufactory (1809 April 1).
John Staples replaced John Clarke as Superintendent of the Virginia Manufactory of Arms around 18 Feb. 1809. Staples provides monthly statements of the operations of the Manufactory from May 1809 to November 1810 (1809 June 6; 1809 July 10; 1809 Aug. 7; 1809 Sept. 6; 1809 Nov. 3; 1809 Nov.; 1809 Dec.; 1810 Jan.; 1810 Feb.; 1810 March; 1810 April; 1810 May; 1810 June; 1810 July; 1810 Aug.; 1810 Sept.; 1810 Oct.; & 1810 Nov.). Staples also furnishes an inventory of pistols & component parts on hand at the Manufactory (1809 March 8); a list of workmen employed at the Armory (1809 Oct. 5); a report of arms distributed from 18 January to 26 October 1809 (1809 Oct. 27); a return of arms at the Manufactory (1810 Nov. 30); and a statement of the operations of the Manufactory from 1 Dec. 1809 to 30 Nov. 1810 (1810 Dec. 24). Staples' correspondence to Governor Tyler includes the following subjects: the procurement of iron in bars rather than scalps (1809 March 15); the appointment of a Keeper of the Arsenal to receive all finished arms (1809 March 21); a room for persons employed at repairing arms (1809 April 10); an estimate of the quantity of lime furnished by Col. John Harvie for the construction of the Armory (1809 April 6); Henry Foxall's works at George Town (1809 April 17); arms for Capt. Christian's Company (1809 April 13); forging bayonets (1809 April 24); the number of arms finished in March & April 1809 (1809 May 9); the number of arms fit for distribution (1809 May 16); component parts of arms on hand when he entered office (1809 May 12); the quantity of ammunition used in proving muskets at the Armory (1809 June 20); short muskets or carbines to be made from burst gun barrels (1809 June 22); the list of balances due the artificers (1809 June 26); the proving of the first gun made by Henry Foxall in the Boring Mill & Foundry (1809 June 29 & July 3); the appropriation for the Foundry & Boring Mill (1809 July 20); the number of arms in the Armory (1809 Nov. 1); lead for the Armory (1809 Nov. 28); the boring of old cannons with a larger caliber (1809 Aug. 10); the salary & duties of George Dabney (1809 Nov. 27); the inspection of arms repaired by Robert Stewart (1809 Dec. 11); a screw press for the General Court Seal (1810 Jan. 8); a finished gun carriage sent to Capitol Square (1810 Jan. 27); bayonets & ramrods for the old guns being repaired by Robert Stewart (1801 March 21); gun carriages (1810 May 22); the quantity of six-pound cannons cast (1810 June 5); George Dabney's claim for extra services rendered (1810 July 12); a commission as major commandant of an Independent Corps of Militia composed of artificers at the Manufactory (includes a list of artificers) (1810 Aug. 7); the casting of cannon (1810 Aug. 15); the repair of arms by Robert Stewart (1810 Aug. 21); a list of cannon cast & mounted (1810 Oct. 31); stocks & ramrods furnished to Robert Stewart for the repair of arms (1810 Oct. 23 & Dec. 10); and a warrant on the Contingent Fund for $5000 for existing claims (1810 Dec. 10).
Abraham Douglas, Keeper of the Penitentiary, communicates with Governor Tyler regarding numerous subjects related to prisoners and the Penitentiary. Douglas provides information to the Governor regarding the conduct of certain prisoners. He encloses inventories of materials, tools, implements, & parts of arms at the Armory (1809 Feb. 20). Douglas writes concerning holsters on hand at the Penitentiary (1809 March 8); a settlement of the profits at the Penitentiary for him & his assistants (1809 March 30); machinery for spinning cotton (1809 May 11 & 20); the erection of a magazine for powder at the Penitentiary (1809 June 13); a proposal by Curtis Carter for building a powder magazine near the Penitentiary (1809 July 6); the price of wrought nails (1809 June 28); capping for the wall around the powder magazine (1809 Oct. 19); the employment of James Roston to conduct the spinning machine at the Penitentiary (1809 Oct. 31); the near completion of the powder magazine by Curtis Carter (1809 Nov. 15); the completion of the magazine except for whitewashing (1809 Nov. 29); the report of the Board of Visitors regarding the profits of the Penitentiary (1810 Jan. 1); proposals for capping the wall outside the magazine (1810 Jan. 30); the account of James Roston (1810 Jan. 25); a report with A. Foster on the plan & estimate of a chapel within the walls of the Penitentiary (1810 Feb. 8); a letter from Joseph A. Myers regarding powder to be delivered to the magazine (1810 Feb. 28); an account of sales of iron & steel (1810 March 7); the sewer at the Penitentiary (1810 April 18); the construction of a new stone sewer (1810 July 18); and nails manufactured at the Penitentiary (1810 Sept. 22).
Philip Norborne Nicholas, Attorney General, writes regarding numerous subjects including an appointment as visitor of the Penitentiary (1809 March 11); the suit against John Clarke (1809 July 31 & 1810 April 24); the bond of Samuel Holmes (1809 Aug. 22); Micajah Crew's appointment to valuate the works at the Armory (1809 Sept. 27); and the Wythe County Court's recommendation of a sheriff (1810 June 28). In addition, the Attorney General provides opinions on the slaves brought into Virginia by the French expelled from Cuba (1809 May 26); the title of the lands owned by the Nottoway Indians (1809 June 22); the laws prohibiting obstructions to the James River (1810 March 27); and the case regarding the state road from the James River to the Kanawha River (1810 Aug. 1).
Daniel L. Hylton & Samuel Coleman, as Clerk & Assistant Clerk of the Council, communicate with the Governor regularly through the Council Office. The Council provides frequent extracts from Council minutes with advice of the Council. A few of the more noteworthy topics include the following: land belonging to the Nottoway Tribe of Indians (1808 Dec. 13); the enforcement of the embargo laws (1809 Jan. 26); arms in possession of the Public Guard including a report of the daily duties performed by the Guard and a return of arms & accoutrements by Peter Crutchfield (1809 Sept. 5); and the repair of widows in the Capitol (1809 Nov.). In addition, Hylton often administered certificates of oath to several state officials including Peyton Randolph as Privy Councilor (1809 Jan. 5); James Jones as Privy Councilor (1809 May 29); William B. Hare as Privy Councilor (1809 May 29); Andrew Reid as Privy Councilor (1809 Dec. 11); Charles K. Mallory & Linah Mims as members of the Privy Council (1811 Jan. 8); and John Tyler as Governor (1810 Dec. 10). Samuel Coleman encloses a statement of the issues of public arms prior to 2 Dec. 1805, since 2 Dec. 1805, the number issued to each regiment, & a statement of public arms by John Clarke (1809 Jan. 19). On 18 July 1810, Coleman requests an increase in salary as a result of the absence of Daniel Hylton.
James Pleasants, Jr., Clerk of the House of Delegates, and Theodosius Hansford, Clerk of the Senate, often submit legislation to the Governor. Hansford encloses a resolution from the Senate regarding the removal of the plastering in the Senate Chamber (1810 Feb. 8). Pleasants & Hansford transmit extracts from the journals of the House of Delegates regarding the elections of John Preston as Treasurer (1809 Jan. 4 & 1810 Jan. 15); Richard Brent as senator in the U.S. Senate (18098 Jan. 7); Joel Leftwich as brigadier general of the 12th Brigade to replace Joseph Martin (1809 Jan. 19); Andrew Moore as major general of the 3rd Division (1809 Jan. 21); Thomas Evans as judge of the General Court (1809 Feb. 10); and James Semple as judge of the General Court to supply the vacancy occasioned by the death of Joseph Prentis (1810 Jan. 31).
Samuel Shepard, Auditor of Public Accounts, corresponds often with Governor Tyler regarding various financial matters. Shepard regularly encloses accounts of expenses for forwarding notices, executions, etc. (1809 May 10; 1809 Aug. 14; 1810 May 10; & 1810 Aug. 21). In addition, Shepard encloses accounts of the Penitentiary with the Commonwealth (1809 May 5; 1810 April 9; & 1810 Dec. 4). Shepard also writes regarding executions levied on personal property returned not sold for want of buyers (1809 March 17); accounts issued to Col. John Harvie & Mr. Rawley for materials for the Manufactory of Arms (1809 April 12); lists of pensioners (1809 May 9 & May 15); warrants issued on the Aggregate Fund for John Harris (1809 May 16); a report on the sources of money to be paid into the Treasury by 1 Nov. and the cause of the present deficit (1809 June 26); the account of George Williamson & William Geddy for iron work done on the Penitentiary buildings (1809 July 11); the account between Adam Baird & the Commonwealth for stone work done on the Manufactory, Foundry, Boring Mill, & for grind stones furnished by him (1809 Aug. 19); accounts from printers of newspapers for publishing certain acts of the Assembly (1809 Sept. 6); vouchers for warrants charged to the U.S. for expenses incurred in the expedition to Norfolk (1809 Nov. 24); accounts between the United States & the Commonwealth (1810 Feb. 13); a statement of debts due the Commonwealth in the District of Agent Andrew Hayes (1810 March 20); dirt among the papers in the presses in consequence of opening the flues in the Auditor's Office & General Court Office (1810 March 20); and an account of the rents received by the agent for the Bristoe Estate (1810 Sept. 21).
Governors from other states comprise a significant amount of correspondence received by the Governor. This correspondence mostly relates to amendments to the U.S. Constitution, extraditions, and the exchange of laws. Included are letters from the following governors: Robert Wright & Edward Lloyd, Maryland; George Truitt, Delaware; Levi Lincoln & Christopher Gore, Massachusetts; David Stone, North Carolina; Simon Snyder, Pennsylvania; Charles Scott, Kentucky; John Trumball & John Treadwell, Connecticut; Samuel Huntington, Ohio; David B. Mitchell, Georgia; Joseph Bloomfield, New Jersey; Jonas Galusha, Vermont; and John Langdon, New Hampshire.
Governor Robert Wright, Maryland, encloses a proclamation for the apprehension of George Gordon (1808 Dec. 30). Afterwards, Governor Edward Lloyd writes acknowledging the receipt of the proceedings of Virginia regarding the amendment proposed by Pennsylvania (1810 Feb. 14). On 3 June 1811, Governor Lloyd transmits a resolution of the state of Maryland against the Pennsylvania amendment for the establishment of an impartial tribunal. Governor George Truitt, Delaware, writes regarding the extradition of Joseph Boughman (1809 Feb. 6). Truitt also transmits a resolution from the Delaware General Assembly against the resolution of Massachusetts concerning embargoes (1810 Feb. 20). Governor Levi Lincoln, Massachusetts, transmits a resolution by the Commonwealth of Massachusetts disapproving of the amendment proposed by Virginia for the removal of senators in Congress by a vote of the state legislature (1809 Feb. 22). Later, Governor Christopher Gore transmits a resolution by the Massachusetts General Assembly proposing an amendment to the Constitution that no law be enacted for laying an embargo for a longer period than thirty days from the commencement of the session of the next Congress (1809 June 21). Governor David Stone, North Carolina, writes regarding his demand for Mins Macklin, a fugitive from justice (1809 March 25). Stone also encloses a copy of the public acts of North Carolina on 9 March 1809 and on 19 March 1810. On 13 July 1809, Governor Stone acknowledges receipt of a map of Virginia and transmits a map of North Carolina. Lastly, Governor Stone writes regarding the requisition for Hampton Wade who was charged with stealing a negro slave (includes bill of indictment) (1810 Aug. 27). Governor Simon Snyder, Pennsylvania, transmits a resolution of the Pennsylvania General Assembly regarding an amendment to the Constitution to establish an impartial tribunal to determine disputes between the general & state governments (1809 April 10). Snyder also writes concerning a fugitive from justice from Virginia (1810 Feb. 3). Governor Charles Scott, Kentucky, encloses a resolution of the Kentucky General Assembly disapproving of the amendment proposed by Virginia for the removal of senators (1809 April 23). Scott also transmits a resolution against another amendment proposed by the state of Pennsylvania (1810 March 27). Governor John Trumball, Connecticut, transmits the new edition of the statute laws of Connecticut (1809 June 2). Following Trumball's governorship, Governor John Treadwell writes regarding receipt of the resolution of Virginia disapproving of the amendment by Pennsylvania for an impartial tribunal (1810 Feb. 22). Governor Samuel Huntington, Ohio, writes respecting a fugitive from justice demanded by Governor Tyler (1810 Jan. 26 & 1810 March 22). In addition, Huntington writes regarding a warrant issued for the arrest of a negro woman named Jane (1810 May 22). Governor David B. Mitchell, Georgia, transmits a copy of a resolution by the Georgia General Assembly disapproving of the resolution of Pennsylvania for an amendment to the Constitution (1810 Feb. 2). Governor Joseph Bloomfield, New Jersey, writes regarding the proposed amendment to the Constitution from the state of Pennsylvania (1810 Feb. 13). Bloomfield also writes respecting the exchange of laws with Virginia (1810 June 8). Lastly, Governor Bloomfield transmits a resolution of the New Jersey General Assembly disapproving of the amendments to the Constitution proposed by Massachusetts, Virginia, & Pennsylvania (1810 Nov. 5). Governor Jonas Galusha, Vermont, transmits a copy of the laws for the state of Vermont (1810 May 22). Finally, Governor John Langdon, New Hampshire, transmits a resolution of the New Hampshire General Assembly in favor of the amendment proposed by the state of Massachusetts regarding embargoes (1810 July 10).